<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A full and true relation of the glorious victory of the Christians over the Turks</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 21 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40594</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2323</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R40980</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">19540387</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 19540387</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109090</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40594)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109090)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1687:35)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A full and true relation of the glorious victory of the Christians over the Turks</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Austro-Turkish War, 1683-1699.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109090:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A FULL and TRUE RELATION OF THE GLORIOUS VICTORY OF THE <hi>CHRISTIANS</hi> over the <hi>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RKS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THe Amazing Progreſſes of the Imperial Arms, being the Preſent Entertainment of the World, and having as yet had no good Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Source, which was the late Great Victory over the</hi> Turks, <hi>We preſum'd it would not be amiſs if we toucht it o'er anew; and the rather for that a moſt particular Relation being come from one of the Principal Officers that was preſent in that Action, it will not only rectify ſeveral Miſtakes that have been committed in moſt of the other Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts that have been Publiſh'd, but give a perfect Idea of that Glorious Battle.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109090:2"/>
            <p>THe Hardſhips ſuffered by the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> as well in going to the Enemies, when they were Encamped under <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> as in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning thence, having as it were ſpent all their Forces, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had no ſooner paſs'd the <hi>Drave</hi> again, but that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail'd with the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> to draw near the <hi>Danube,</hi> where Proviſions could not be ſo ſcarce as in the Parts whence they came. This was a Courſe ſo neceſſary for the Army, that there was no other way to reſcue it from abſolute Ruine; the Cavalry, more eſpecially, had been in want of Forrage for above a Month, for having been almoſt continually in the Moeraſſes, it had had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubſiſtence than what they afforded.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Turks</hi> knowing it's Diſtreſs, and being alſo encourag'd by what had befall'n them near <hi>Eſſeck,</hi> they march'd after it. In the mean while, the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> got to <hi>Mohatz,</hi> where they ſtaid eight whole days to recover themſelves of their Fatigues. There the <hi>Danube</hi> furniſh'd them with abundance of Proviſions, and their Army being in ſome wiſe recover'd, a Council of War was held to conſult on what undertaking it ſhould be employed. Herein it was reſolv'd that <hi>Alba-Regalis</hi> ſhould be Beſieged, and that they ſhould immediately begin their March to execute this Deſign. During theſe Tranſactions, ſome Parties of <hi>Tartars</hi> advanc'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der favour of the Woods, and ſnapt up our Forragers. The next day they did the ſame again, and our Spies brought back word that the whole <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Army was at hand, and was moving on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with Intention of Beleaguering <hi>Ziclos.</hi> A Deſerter and a Priſoner, taken by a Party, Confirm'd this Report; whereupon a new Council of War was held, the Reſult of which was to demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>Ziclos</hi> and <hi>Five-Churches,</hi> take the Garriſons thence, and all that was within them, and then to march on to <hi>Alba-Regalis,</hi> where we were in hopes of making good Lines before the <hi>Turks</hi> could come up to us. On the 8th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> we left <hi>Mohatz</hi> to put this Deſign in Execution, but we had no ſooner began our March, but that there appeared a Body of full three thouſand Horſe, that advanced very near us, which compell'd us to halt. It Skirmiſh'd in good Order, inſomuch as to hinder the Army from getting that day to the place where the D. of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had deſign'd to Encamp. Thus it ſtopp'd within half a League above <hi>Mohatz,</hi> where the Spies not only Confirm'd the News they had brought the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but further that the <hi>Grand-Vizier</hi> had ſo efficaciouſly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> that he was in a Condition to fight the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that he had received Orders to give Battle. The
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109090:2"/> Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> imparted theſe News to the Elector of <hi>Bavariae</hi> and the General Officers, who did not Queſtion the Truth of the Information, ſeeing with what Boldneſs the three thouſand Horſe had ſtopp'd them the day before. Nevertheleſs they perſiſted in the Deſign they had projected, and Orders were given for the continuing the March on the morrow. In the mean while, part of the Night was ſpent in ſending out Parties, and in Clearing our Arms. The Parties gave not any Account on which any Reliance could be had, but a Spye that had been in the <hi>Turks</hi> very Camp, brought back word, that the <hi>Grand-Vizier</hi> had caus'd the Orders he had received from <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to be proclaimed throughout the whole Camp, with a promiſe of rewarding all thoſe that ſhould behave themſelves as became them in the Battle. The <hi>Imperial</hi> Army having renew'd it's March at break of day, it was again diſturb'd by a Body of Horſe, that did not diſcontinue Skirting it, and ever and anon coming up to try it's temper. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> drew up Forces to receive them, but they made ſo very Orderly a Retreat, that there was no way to get them to an Engagement. This paſs'd on the 9th of the Month, and the Enemies Conduct was ſtill the ſame on the 10th and 11th, ſtill following the Army that was marching towards <hi>Ziclos.</hi> At laſt the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> being come that day near the Hill of <hi>Herſan,</hi> at the foot of which was formerly a fine Village bearing the ſame name, but which War has totally ruined, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> had notice that the <hi>Grand-Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zier</hi> after having march'd Day and Night, had made ſuch expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that he was but a League diſtant from him, nay that he had poſſeſs'd himſelf of a Wood that was on his way, and wherein he had put ſome Troups, hoping to fall upon his in the Flank. As nothing was to be neglected with ſuch an Enemy, that ſince the beginning of the Campagne had exerted ſuch great Skill and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience as was not to have been expected in the <hi>Turks,</hi> it was thought expedient to call a Council of War anew: It was the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector of <hi>Bavaria</hi>'s turn to Command the Vanguard the next day; but as it was dangerous to make ſuch a Movement, it was reſolv'd, contrary to what is commonly practic'd in a March, that every one ſhould remain at the Poſt where he was the day before. We again ſent out ſeveral Parties, but of few men only, to know exactly whether what was ſaid of the Enemy was true; but the Enemy on his ſide being not willing to lye ſtill, ſent two or three thouſand Horſe that very Evening, which gave an Allarum to the Camp. As the whole Army ſtood at their Arms, it was impoſſible for them to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109090:3"/> do any thing, on the contrary they were drove back to the very Thickets, and we durſt not puſh them further, as fearing there might be ſome conſiderable Succours behind the Buſhes. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> to be aſcertain'd of this, caus'd Men to climb up to the Hill of <hi>Herſan,</hi> and they bringing him word that there appeared a great Body beyond the Thickets; ſome Voluntiers advanc'd to fire their Piſtols at them; but not being ſo advantageouſly moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as many of the <hi>Turks</hi> they went to attacque, they were imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately Surrounded, and their Heads hewn off in the preſence of the whole Army. This was done with ſuch fearfull howlings, that it daunted all thoſe that had not yet been Engag'd with thoſe Barbarians. In the mean while, each Man withdrew into his Camp, and as it was not queſtion'd but that there would be a conſiderable Bruſh the next day, the Greater part of the Generals ſpent the Night on Horſeback, and towards break of day the Enemies came to Surprize and take away the main Guard. Some Blows were given in this Occaſion, but the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> being in a due Poſture, they kill'd 5 or 6 <hi>Turks</hi> for as many of theirs which ſell upon the Place. One of thoſe Barbarians who was not yet Dead, having been queſtion'd, ſaid that the <hi>Grand-Vizier</hi> was there hard by with his Army, conſiſting of Seaventy thouſand Men, that he had been Retrenching himſelf all the Night, that he had alſo lin'd the Wood, above mention'd, with more Men, that he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended he was ſo advantageouſly Encamp'd, that he bragg'd he ſhould defeat the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Army, without being compell'd to give Battle. Hereupon a Council of War was held a-new, and as the falling back would have been the abandoning of <hi>Zyclos</hi> and the other Places on the <hi>Drave,</hi> they agreed to purſue their march to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the former of thoſe Places. The Orders having accordingly been given, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> put himſelf at the head of the Vanguard, which was compoſed of the Right Wing, and that he might be under Cover from the Enemies that were in the Wood, he left ſome Dragoons and Battaillons to cover the flank of the Horſe. The Enemies lying at watch to take their Advantages, made then a Movement which perplex'd the Duke of <hi>Lorrain;</hi> He perceiv'd that they were going to fall upon the Duke of <hi>Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria;</hi> wherefore he Detach'd <hi>Picolomini</hi> with his Brigade to go give him Succours. And indeed they began to Skirmiſh with that Duke, who advancing to encourage his Men by his Preſence, a <hi>Turk</hi> ſlipt along under ſavour of the Buſhes, and ſeeing the Elector have a Red-Embroidered Coat on, with a white feather
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109090:3"/> in his Hat, and thence preſuming him to be a Perſon of Quality, he fancy'd it would be a Brave Exploit in him to kill him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he fired his Fuſil at him, but inſtead of hitting him in the Body, he hit him in the left hand, and this made ſo much noiſe that all thoſe that were not far from his Perſon believed him to be dangerouſly wounded. Without farther Enquiry this ſame ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour was immediately ſpread about his Troups, and this might have been of ill Conſequence, had he not ſhewn himſelf immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to them all.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, the Army being on its march, and the Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard having paſs'd a Bottom, it mov'd up along a furrow, at the Upper End of which there was a Hedge that covered a Plain; Beyond this Hedge were ſome <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Horſe, which were to amuſe the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> while the main Body fell upon the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> made a ſhew as if they meant to come to Blows with him; but having avoided the Battle at the ſame time they ſeem'd to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it: the whole ſtreſs fell upon the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who having orders not to Engage, contented himſelf with ſtanding upon the Defenſive. This did ſtill the more Embolden the Infidels, and coming up very cloſe and every other moment to try his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, he ſent to acquaint the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> with the Poſture of his Affairs, and to ask his leave to fight. The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſent him back word to follow the Orders they had agreed on in the Morning, but his Electoral Highneſs ſeeing himſelf ſtill more and more preſs'd, ſent back to tell the Duke of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> that when they were in a Council of War, they might argue as they pleas'd, but that when the Enemies were pouring upon them the caſe was very Different; that every other minute there fell-upon him new Battaillons and new Squadrons, which it was impoſſible for him to ſtand the Brunt of, by meerly keeping upon the Defenſive, that his Men being thereby Expoſed, began to murmur at ſo much prudence; that it was to be feared that after their having ſuffer'd much, they might take the Courſe of avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Danger by flight, ſince poſſibly they would imagine they might honourably do ſo, ſince we led 'em not on to fight.</p>
            <p>During theſe Occurrences the Number of the Infidels did viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly multiply, and having ſlipt along a Wood, they wholly fac'd it, inſomuch that when the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> came to paſs, they made a Diſcharge upon them, which laid ſome of them upon the ſpot, and compell'd the Reſt to halt. To perplex them the more, they appeared at the ſame time at the Vanguard, but their Deſign being
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109090:4"/> to make their utmoſt Onſets on the ſide of the Elector of <hi>Bavaria;</hi> They proceeded no further then to Skirmiſh, which hindred the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> from being able to ſend other Snccours than that before-mentioned to the Reer. In the mean while, as every thing till then had promis'd them the Victory, a Body that had not as yet fall'n on, advanc'd the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> with diſmal ſcreams and howlings, inſomuch that he ſaw himſelf thereby forc'd, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtaying for the Permiſſion he had to demand to fight, to uſe his utmoſt Endeavours to free himſelf from ſo great a danger. He made head againſt them with ſuch Troups as in whom he moſt Confided, and having caus'd ſmall Field-Pieces to be plac'd at the head of the Battaillons, they were put to ſo good a uſe that they kept the Enemies in great Reſpect. In the mean while, <hi>Picolomini,</hi> who, as has been ſaid, was ſent to the Duke of <hi>Bavaria's</hi> Succours, thinking him in great Danger, ran to him with his Men, and the Duke ſeeing him come, Commanded him to drive the <hi>Turks</hi> from a Bottom, which he had newly paſſed himſelf. <hi>Picolomini</hi> execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this Order with great Courage, and being ſeconded by good Fortune, he not only remained Maſter of the Bottom, but alſo purſued the Enemies to the very Wood, which they ſtill poſſeſs'd, and which was the place of their Retreat. There they perceived that they had unaccountably given way, ſince he had none to back him; Inſomuch that being aſhamed of what they had done, they returned to the Charge, and made ſuch havock of the Regiment of <hi>Commerci,</hi> which was of that Brigade, that in a trice they killed two hundred of it's men. The reſt ſeeing this, betook themſelves to flight, and the ſooner for that they were all terrified to ſee theſe <hi>Barbarians,</hi> who had cut off the heads of the greater part, which they carried before them, howling at ſuch a rate as was capable of daunting the moſt Reſolute. In this Occaſion was it that the Prince of <hi>Commerci</hi> was wounded with a Launce, and that the Count <hi>de Ligneville,</hi> the Major of his Regiment was killed, whoſe Head they cut off as well as the reſt. The reſt of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Cavalry, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this advantage on it's ſide, fell then anew with extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fury upon the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> who was not a little put to it to ſtand this firſt Onſet; Nevertheleſs having of his own Perſon performed Wonders, and thereby given an Example to others, they all ſtood firm; Inſomuch that after a long and very obſtinate fight the <hi>Turks</hi> began to Buckle; but in ſuch good order, that in turning their backs they ſeem'd leſs to Fly then make a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat. This induced the Elector to conſider whether he ought to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109090:4"/> purſue them or not; but that held him not long in ſuſpence, they of themſelves return'd to the Charge, and that too with ſo much Reſolution and Fury, that had not the Elector commanded Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non to be brought, they had been Capable of routing him. But having caus'd it to be charg'd with Cartridges, he diſperſed the moſt daring. An infinite number of Volleys were fired in a trice, and this with ſo much Succeſs, that we heard the Cries of thoſe that were wounded by them, which did ſo very much intimidate the reſt, that they betook themſelves to flight. They retired aſide the Wood, which put a ſtop for ſome time, apprehending it might be lin'd, and that inſtead of proſecuting a Victory, we might hazzard the receiving an Affront. In the mean while, the Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> having caus'd it to be view'd, and none of them being there found, we purſued them, but the Purſuit was not long. After we had march'd a very little time we perceived they had entred into Retrenchments, which we could not believe tho' we ſaw it with our Eyes. Theſe Retrenchments had indeed been made in haſt, and we ſaw they had not had time to compleat them: But as their ſcituation was advantageous (for they were between a Moeraſs and a Wood) it was not judg'd convenient to advance further, without firſt uſing mature conſideration. We perceived it to be the <hi>Grand-Viziers</hi> Camp, which was confirm'd to us by ſome Priſoners, who inform'd us that there were ſtill ſeveral freſh forces that had not as yet ſtirr'd out of it. This occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd new thoughts, as alſo for that the head of this Camp was defended by a Battery of twelve Pieces of Ordinance, which began to ſpeak to us in Thunder. It was ſtill further augmented in a Moment, and the <hi>Turks</hi> fearing that the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> would undertake to force them, notwithſtanding ſo many difficulties, fell to work in our very ſight to ſtop up ſome Paſſages that were as yet quite open. Nay, and we perceiv'd a Man with a Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant all beſet with Jewels, and a ſtately Veſtment give his Orders without ſeeming to be under the leaſt Concern. We judg'd as well by this Character as from the Richneſs of the things newly mention'd, that if it was not the <hi>Grand-Vizier,</hi> it was at leaſt a Perſon of very great Eminency among them. This aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the Greedineſs of the Soldiery, who being vex'd that they had fought ſo long without having got any thing, ask'd why they ſtopp'd at ſuch ſmall Impediments. The Elector was altogether of the ſame Opinion, but the General Officers about him having given him to underſtand that the undertaking to force thoſe Retrenchments without Cannon, would be too great
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109090:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> a venture, ſeveral Pieces were brought up, which were plac'd Battery-wiſe with wonderfull Expedition. The greater part of the Retrenchment being only of Dirt and Mud, having been hereby Levell'd in a trice, all of a Sudden we ſaw the Cavalry march, without ſtaying for Orders, telling each other that if they could but paſs, they were enrich'd for Ever. That of the <hi>Turks</hi> ſeeing it coming with ſo much Reſolution grew daunted, and without ſtaying for its coming up, fled cowardly away, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoning the Infantry to the Diſcretion of the Conquerors. The <hi>Janizaries</hi> were ſtartled at the Deſertion of their Horſe, nevertheleſs they march'd up to the Breach, which they defended with ſuch Courage as was near a-kin to deſpair. But the Cavalry having open'd it ſelf a paſſage thro' other Places, they were quickly Surrounded and put to the Sword. The Reſt of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantry ſuffer'd very much, and none Eſcap'd but the moſt ready at their heels. All the Tents were found in the Camp, which the Elector having entred made directly up to that of the <hi>Grand-Vizier,</hi> which was obſervable for its Extraordinary wealth, and for ſeveral marks which are peculiar to the Generals of thoſe <hi>Barbarians.</hi> He found no body in it, nor about it, tho' it was well worth the pains of looking to, as well in regard of its ſelf, as of what it contain'd.</p>
            <p>In the mean while, the Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> advanc'd, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemented his Electoral Highneſs upon the happy Succeſs of that Day; but having not leiſure to enlarge much upon that, he gave <hi>Dunewaldt</hi> Order to purſue the Runaways, and detach'd Ten thouſand Horſe for that Expedition. This Gen. found ſome of the Fugitives on the way, but making directly to the Bridge which the <hi>Turks</hi> had o're the <hi>Drave,</hi> he found the main Body had paſs'd it, and had broke the Bridge after them. But the ſhore was all ſtrew'd with Cloaths, and Bodies lay all floating o're the River. Two <hi>Baſſa's,</hi> and ſeveral of the Principal Officers were taken Priſoners, with about Eight hundred Common Soldiers, and the Dead ten times as many. The Conquerors got all the Cannon, conſiſting in Ninety pieces of Ordinance, and twelve Mortar-pieces, with Tents, Camels, Waggons, and Elephants in Abundance, with all other ſorts of Booty allmoſt beyond Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. This Victory coſt the <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> not above ſix Hundred Men, as they themſelves ſay, and as others Eighteen hundred. And thus ended that Glorious Day, for which <hi>Te Deum</hi> was ſung in the Camp, at <hi>Vienna, Rome,</hi> and <hi>Venice.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>Modern Hiſtory, <hi>Or the</hi> Monethly Accounts <hi>of all Conſiderable Occurrences,</hi> Civil, Eccleſiaſtical, <hi>and</hi> Military. <hi>Sold by</hi> R. Taylor</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:109090:5"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
